Guide to the Concerned Residents of the Youghiogheny Records, 1968-2004 AIS.2004.14
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Concerned Residents of the Youghiogheny Records
1968-2004
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Concerned Residents of the Youghiogheny
AIS.2004.14
41.25 Linear Feet (27 boxes, 1 oversize file)
Concerned Residents of the Youghiogheny (CRY) was a grassroots environmental organization that existed from 1985 to 1998 in Yukon, Pennsylvania, an unincorporated village in South Huntingdon Township. CRY worked to close down a nearby toxic waste disposal site owned by Mill Service, Inc., start cleanup and relocation programs, and to change legislation concerning waste management. The records include meeting minutes, correspondence, legal briefs, photographs, newspaper clippings, reports of surveys, posters, and videotapes. They show the progress and results of the group's efforts, including extensive public awareness campaigns, litigation, interaction with local and state government, and cooperation with other environmental groups.
History
Concerned Residents of the Youghiogheny (CRY) - also referred to as Concerned Residents of Yukon and the Youghiogheny - was a grassroots environmental organization that attempted to close down a toxic waste dump in Yukon, Pennsylvania from 1985 to 1998. Yukon is an unincorporated village located in South Huntingdon Township, Westmoreland County, inhabited mostly by retired industrial workers, many of whom live on fixed incomes in this rural community. In 1963, Mill Service, Inc. opened a hazardous waste disposal facility in Yukon. This facility disposed of strong acids used in steel production referred to as "pickle liquors," along with other waste products from industry, by storing them in large open pits called "impoundments" or "lagoons." These lagoons were dug over abandoned mine tunnels, which then drained into local streams and groundwater.
Beginning in the mid 1970s, residents of Yukon had complained of abnormally high rates of cancers and other ailments, as well as dying cattle, in their community. Individual attempts to alert local government officials brought unsatisfactory results, and in September of 1985 Yukon residents Nick and Angie Babich, Melbry Bolk, and Diana Steck decided to form a permanent organization while attending a conference held by the Citizens' Clearinghouse for Hazardous Wastes (CCHW). In October of that year, CRY was organized in Yukon at a town meeting and was incorporated as a non-profit organization shortly thereafter. CRY worked to close down Mill Service, Inc.'s Yukon disposal site, start cleanup and relocation programs, and change legislation concerning waste management. They pursued these goals through public awareness campaigns, government liaison efforts, community health tests and surveys, litigation, and grassroots outreach and fundraising. CRY also pioneered the first recycling program in Westmoreland County and trained many new environmental organizations in the western Pennsylvania region.
At times, CRY seemed close to achieving some of their goals, but their larger objectives were ultimately frustrated. The health of many members declined due to illnesses they attributed to the hazardous wastes, and some moved out of the area to escape the pollution. A unique challenge surfaced in 1997 when the Ku Klux Klan set up an office in Yukon and offered to help fight against Mill Service Inc. in an attempt to gain recruits. CRY led the community in a successful resistance against the Klan, which was their last accomplishment. The strain of that crisis was too much for the weakened group, and by 1998 CRY had effectively disbanded.
One member, Ed Collins, continued to pursue related aims on his own through 2004, and records of these are included in Series II. CRY's legacy endures in other ways: they formed the Pennsylvania Environmental Network as an alliance with other local grassroots environmental groups, including: Pennsylvanians United to Rescue the Environment, Citizens Against Toxic Sites, Group Against Smog and Pollution, and Kiski Valley Coalition to Save Our Children. At the national level, they also worked with organizations such as Greenpeace and kept up a close relationship with the Citizens' Clearinghouse for Hazardous Wastes.
In 1995, Mill Service, Inc. was consolidated with Allegheny Liquid Systems under the new name of MAX Environmental Technologies.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into eleven series:
Series I: Minutes
Series II: Office Files
Series III: Health and Environmental Testing
Series IV: Mill Service, Inc. and Environmental Pollution
Series V: Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection (DEP), formerly Department of Environmental Resources (DER)
Series VI: Litigation
Series VII: News Releases and Newspaper Clippings
Series VIII: Files from the office of Pa. Representative Manderino
Series IX: Medical Records [RESTRICTED]
Series X: Posters
Series XI: Videotapes
Scope and Content Notes
The records in this collection cover the full duration of CRY's existence and represent the entirety of its activities. They show how the individual members and the group as a whole operated in pursuing their mission: how they organized themselves, gathered and used information, collaborated and negotiated with other agencies, and faced the challenges of limited resources and opposing government and business interests. Types of records include meeting minutes, correspondence, legal briefs, photographs, newspaper clippings, reports of surveys, posters, and videotapes. Many subjects and activities are represented across multiple files and series. Researchers should search the collection widely.
Access Restrictions
In order to protect the privacy of individuals involved, and in compliance with the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (HIPAA), Series IX. Medical Records are closed to researchers until further notice.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Diana Steck (former president of CRY), August 2004.
Previous Citation
Concerned Residents of the Youghiogheny Records, 1976-2001, AIS.2004.14, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Westmoreland County (Pa.); Yukon (Pa.); Hazardous waste sites -- Pennsylvania -- Westmoreland County; Environment; Environmentalists -- Pennsylvania -- Westmoreland County; Environmentalism -- Pennsylvania -- Westmoreland County; Thornburgh, Dick; Kukovich, Allen G.; Babich, Angie; Babich, Nick; Bolk, Melbry; Casey, Robert P. (Robert Patrick); Citizen's Clearinghouse for Hazardous Wastes (Arlington, Va.); Collins, Ed; Concerned Residents of the Youghiogheny; Manderino, James J.; MAX Environmental Technologies; Mill Service, Inc; Pennsylvania Environmental Network; Specter, Arlen; Steck, Diana
- Minutes, 1985-1997; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Minutes from regular meetings, executive board meetings, and special meetings are filed together. Regular meetings were held on the second Monday of each month, Executive Board meetings were held weekly, and special meetings were called when situations arose that needed immediate attention from the members of the group. Minutes are arranged chronologically by year. Hand-written notes from some meetings and some financial reports are also found in this series.
  - Minutes, 1985-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
  - Hand-written notes from meetings, 1985-1997 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
- Office Files, 1974-2004; II.
  The bulk of this series comes from files which were kept in the CRY office. All of the main concerns of the organization are represented in this series, often under more than one heading. It also contains incomplete samples of financial records (mostly accounting ledgers), and information about CRY's status as a charitable organization, including the strategies they used for fundraising. There are records of specific activities and protests organized to raise public awareness, and many files containing writings of individual members, filed under their surnames. Other contents include research files on subjects relevant to the group's mission, administrative and operational records, and information about other environmental activist organizations, including the Pennsylvania Environmental Network and the Citizens' Clearinghouse for Hazardous Wastes. The files dealing with legislative acts do not contain copies of the acts themselves.
  - Accounting Ledgers, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Activities (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Addresses (CRY Members) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Addresses (Yukon) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Affidavit of Appeal (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Alice Watershed (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Air (Indoor) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Air Quality (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Air Quality Services, Ltd. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ammunition Against DER and MS (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Annual Reports (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Anto (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Application for Solid Waste Disposal Permit (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Appraisers - Julian Fine (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Articles of Incorporation (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Arway, John - Fisheries Biologist (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - ATSDR (Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - ATSDR - Nov 18, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Attendance Sheets (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Attorney General Preate (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Auditor General (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Babich (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Barauskas III Joseph Report (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bazala (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Berman Report (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bingo (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - BFI (Browning-Ferris Industries, Inc.) (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Birthday Balloon Launch (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Board Members (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bolef, Dan (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
  - Bolef, Dan: Notes for Extended Treatment of Law Forum Article (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bolef, Dan: DER Protocols (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Bolk family (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Budget Information (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bulger, Pa. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Bulk Mailing Information (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - Bullfrog Films (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - By-Laws (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Capitol Building Map and Directions (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Casey, Governor - Relocation, etc. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Casey Form Letters (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Casey Letters (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Casey Wanted Posters (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Casey X (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - CATS (Citizens Against Toxic Sites) (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - CCHW (Citizens' Clearinghouse for Hazardous Wastes) (Box 2, Folder 36-38)
  - Cement Kilns (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Certificate of Achievement (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chambers, Atwoods (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Charitable Organization status (including small games of chance) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - CHD (Campaign for Human Development) Grants, 1986-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5-17)
  - Chelation (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Chem Nuclear Systems, Inc. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Chemical Information (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Citizens' Advisory Council to DER, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Citizens' Complaint Forms (DER) (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
  - Citizens' Complaints of Dust Clouds (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Clarion - Directions to (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Cleanup Options (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Clinton-Gore, letters to (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Closure #5 - Misc. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Coburn Case - Attorney Albert J. Slapp (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Collins, Ed (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Collins, Ed: Post-CRY Files, Last Gasps, 1996-2004 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Collins, Ed: Post-CRY Files, Clinic, 1996-2004 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Collins, Ed: Post-CRY Files, DEP, 1996-2004 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Collins, Ed: Post-CRY Files, Public Participation, 1996-2004 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Collins, Ed: Post-CRY Files, Dave Kodrin (PEN, Grants), 1996-2004 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Collins, Ed: Post-CRY Files, Yukon Community Clinic Letter, 1996-2004 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Commissioners' Meeting, February 25, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Community Organization (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Compost Patch (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Consent Order, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Consent Orders (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Conservation Report - Camille George (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Contacts (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Contaminants (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Contaminated Homes - Memo, August 1985 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Cookbook Information (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence - General (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence - Government (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - County Commissioners (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - CRY Core Files (Box 4, Folder 28-30)
  - CRY - CNN (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - CRY - Early '87, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - CRY - What It Is (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - CWAP (Clean Water Action Project) (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - DER Shutdown of MS, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - De-watering of Western Lagoon #6 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Dickinson College (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Dioxin Treatment (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - DUQ (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Duritsa "Hanging" (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Earth Day (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
  - Emergency Evacuation Plan, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Emissions (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Envirite Corporation (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Environmental Health Network (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - EHB (Environmental Hearing Board) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Environmental Organizations (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Environmental Pamphlets (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Environmental Task Force (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Environmental Testing (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - EQB and Citing Criteria (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - FASE (Foundation for Achievments in Science and Education) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Fiberglass and Cancer (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Fluoride Toxicity (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Free-COL Labs: Analytical Report (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - GASP (Group Against Smog and Pollution) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Geology Reports (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Gibbs - Photo (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Global Warming Watch (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Golf Tournament, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Grants (Box 5, Folder 19-22)
  - Greenpeace (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Groundwater (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Groundwater Conference Notes (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Guest Speakers - Bios (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Harper, Barbara (DER Toxicologist) (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Harris, Glen (Clippings) (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Hazardous Materials Incident Reports (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Health (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Health Clinic (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Inspection Reports (Box 5, Folder 32-33)
  - Japanese Information of Hazardous Waste (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Jewish Healthcare Foundation (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Kautz, Tim and Sandy (Box 5, Folder 36-37)
  - King, Linda (Compiled by Dan Bolef) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Kiwanis (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Korber, Diane (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Kostmayer, Peter H. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Kukovich, Allen (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Lagoon #5 - Closure (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Landfills - Existing and Proposed (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
  - Lappe Report Proof (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Letters (Health - from Doctors) (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Letters to Editor (Tribune Review) (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Liner Information (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Love Canal (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - LuLu Dilemma (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Manderino (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Mihalich, Herman (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - McDonald Report (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
  - McToxins - Styrofoam (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Media Information (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Medical Waste (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Member Lists (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Mill Service Customer List (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Mill Service Expansion - Map (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Mine Permit Information - DER (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Miranda, Dr. (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Municipal Landfill - Pa. Permit Procedure (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Municipal Waste Information (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Murphy, Austin J. (Information prepared for) (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Newsletters (Box 6, Folder 30-31)
  - Nuclear Accidents and Safety (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Office Staff (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Ometz, Lewis (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Omni Report (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Organizations and their Member Addresses (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Organizing Information (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Pathway - Bazala's, 2/5/94 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - PCB's (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - PEN (Pennsylvania Environmental Network) (Box 6, Folder 40-44)
  - Pennsylvania State Study - Revitalization of Coal Mine Areas (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Permit #6 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Pesticides (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Petitions, Signed (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Phelps, Gail (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Political Letters (Box 7, Folder 6-8)
  - Polluter of the Month Award (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
  - Polluters Plan (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Popular Epidemiology (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Pornography Shop (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Poster Contest (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Project Planning Out Time (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Public Hearing/Proposal Facility (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
  - Public Relations (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - PUC Information (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Putting the Heat on Polluters (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Quarterly Reports, 1986-1993 (Box 7, Folder 21-24)
  - Questions to Ask (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Radioactive Waste (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - RCRA (Resource Conservation and Recovery Act) Reports, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 27-28)
  - Real Estate Information (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Recycling (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Regulating Low Level Radioactive Waste in Pa. (DER meeting) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Relocation (Box 8, Folder 2-4)
  - Residual Waste Beneficial Use Approvals - Mill Service (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Resignations - CRY Board Members (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Right to Know Information (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Rupp, David and Carol (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Rupp, Ray (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Resolution - Westmoreland County Commissioners (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - SARA - Title III (Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Act) (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Seton Hill Information (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Sierra Club (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Siting Criteria (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Skits (Box 8, Folder 15-16)
  - "SLAPPy" Company index (Strategic Lawsuits Against Public Participation) (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Soil Sampling Plan - DER (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Solid Waste Disposal Act (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Solid Waste Permit #301671 - Minor Permit Modification (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Songsheets (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - South Huntingdon Cancer Mortality Rate (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - South Huntington Supervisor, Hempfield Mill Service Water Lines (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Specter, Arlen (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Steck, Diana, including correspondence (Box 8, Folder 25-27)
  - Stewardship (Christian ecological ministry) (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Strahl, Frank and Gretchen (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Stress Workshop Notes (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Superfund (Box 8, Folder 31-32)
  - Sweeper Bag Tests (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Sworn Statements (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Take Pride in America 7th National Awards Program (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Three-Mile Island (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Thornburgh, Governor (Box 8, Folder 37-38)
  - Tolerance and Civil Rights (Ku Klux Klan invasion and protest), 1997 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - Town Meeting, 1/31/91 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Toxic Chemicals (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Toxological Evaluation (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - User Fees (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
  - Violations, Notice of - DER (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Waste Codes (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Waste Management, Inc. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Waste Reduction (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Water Information (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Westinghouse, Incinerator, Research Permit (Box 9, Folder 14-16)
  - Wetlands (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Wofford, Senator (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Yearly Reports (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Yough School District Farm (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Yukon Site History (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Zoning and Planning (Box 9, Folder 22-23)
- Health and Environmental Testing, III.
  The possibility of compensation for the residents of Yukon for health damages rested mainly on the results of a DER-commissioned health study of South Huntingdon Township, in which Yukon is located. This study was conducted from 1986 to 1988. Several other tests and surveys were conducted around the Yukon area in order to determine the extent of pollution coming from the dump site and the effects of the pollution on the health of residents. Some were conducted by the DER and some were commissioned by CRY from independent contractors in hopes that the results would provide more conclusive evidence to support the group's claims in court. Additional documentation of other environmental tests can be found in series IV.
  - Air Tests of Homes (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Animal Testing (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Basement Test (ATSDR), 1991 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Citizens' Environmental Lab - Reports (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Cokeburg and Yukon Health Studies (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Cancer Study Information (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Cancer Mortality in South Huntingdon Township (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Cancer and Other Diseases (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Comments of CCHW - Health Survey (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Diana's Family Health (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Dr. Miranda (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Environmental Testing, various (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Epidemiology Studies (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
  - Health Departments - Correspondence (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
  - Health, Pa. Department of (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Health Effects of Toxic Chemicals (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Health File (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Health Questionnaire (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Health Replies from Doctors (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Health Studies and Surveys (Box 10, Folder 17-21)
  - Industrial Testing (Texaco) (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - K-Chem Lab Testing - Kodrin (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Lappe, Dr. M, Health Report (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous Tests - Sources Not Named (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Mortality Rate in Yukon (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Robertson, Greg (DER) - Testing Methods (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Soil Tests (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - VOC (Box 10, Folder 29-30)
  - Water Tests (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Drinking Water Tests - Domestic Wells (Box 10, Folder 32-36)
  - Groundwater Tests, Mill Service (Box 11, Folder 1-9)
  - Yukon Health Study (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Yukon Mortality and Death Certificates (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Mill Service, Inc. and Environmental Pollution, IV.
  Many of the records in this series specifically relate to permits granted to Mill Service by the Department of Environmental Resources (DER), and the monitoring of their procedures and operations in order to detect pollution and safety hazards. Mill Service's Yukon facility and a separate facility in Bulger, Pa. were repeatedly found to be in violation of permit terms over their years of operation. In 1985, the DER issued Consent Orders for the two facilities, which allowed their continued operations, providing proof of Mill Service's on-going actions to redress past and current environmental pollution. A copy of this consent order can be found in Series VI (Litigation). Much of the series also documents the plan, proposed by Mill Service, Inc. in 1985, to close one of the waste lagoons, Impoundment No. 5, and the creation in 1987 of a new lagoon, Impoundment No. 6, by a combination of strip mining and blasting.
  - Allegheny Ludlum Pickle Liquor (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Assessment Charge - Mill Service (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Attachments - Plans for waste impoundments (Box 11, Folder 14-22)
  - Bender, Carl - letters from (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Benefit Fee Reports, 1989-1990 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Blast Proposal Notice (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Bulger (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Case Studies (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Chemical Analysis of Different Companies and Consultant Reports (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Civil Penalty Payment $250,000 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Closure Cost Estimates (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Closure Info (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Closure Plan #5 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Compliance History Form C (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - Closure #6 Final Design Report (Box 11, Folder 34)
  - Construction #6 (Box 11, Folder 35)